<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr Penn with his answer.</title>
            <author>Popple, William, d. 1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2964A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617505</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2729:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr Penn with his answer.</title>
                  <author>Popple, William, d. 1708.</author>
                  <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrew Sowle and are to be sold by the several booksellers in London ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1688].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Published anonymously. Authorship from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Letter by Popple dated: October the 20th. 1688; answer by Penn dated: October the 24th. 1688.</note>
                  <note>A letter to William Penn offering him advice about his relations in the royal court and response by Penn on matter of freedom of religion.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page cropped at lower margin with loss of part of imprint and date of publication.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
                  <note>To the Honourable William Penn Esq. Proprietor and Governour of Pensylvania -- Mr. Penn's answer to the foregoing letter.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> PENN WITH His Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> And are to be Sold by the ſeveral Bookſellers in <hi>London</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:175324:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175324:2"/>
            <head>To the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ourable William Penn <abbr>Eſq.</abbr> Proprietor and Governour OF PENSYLVANIA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RED SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO the Friendſhip, with which you are pleaſed to honour me, doth afford me ſufficient opportunities of Diſcourſing with you upon any Subject, yet I chuſe rather at this time to offer unto you, in Writing, ſome reflections which have occur'd to my Thoughts, in a matter of no common Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The Importance of it doth primarily and directly reſpect your ſelf, and your own private Concernments: But it alſo conſequentially and effectually regards the King, his Government, and even the peace and ſettlement of this whole Nation. I intreat you therefore to bear with me, if I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in this manner, to give ſomewhat more weight unto mywords, than would be in a tranſtient Diſcourſe, and leave them with you as a Subject that requires your retired Conſideration.</p>
            <p>You are not ignorant that the part you are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have had of late Years in publick Affairs, tho without either the <hi>Title,</hi> or <hi>Honour,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> of any Publick Office, and that eſpecially your avowed endeavours to introduce amongſt us a general and inviolable <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in matters of <hi>Meer Religion,</hi> have occaſioned the miſtakes of ſome Men, provoked the malice of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and, in the end, have raiſed againſt you a multitude of Enemies, who have unworthily defamed you with ſuch Imputations as I am ſure you abhor. This I know you have been ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed off, tho' I doubt you have not made ſufficient reflection upon it. The Conſciouſneſs of your own Innocence ſeems to me to have given you too great a contempt of ſuch unjuſt and ill-grounded Slanders. For however glorious it is, and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, for a truly Virtuous Mind, whoſe inward Peace is founded upon that Rock of Innocence, to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the empty noiſe of popular Reproach, yet even that Sublimity of Spirit may ſometimes ſwell to a reprovable Exceſs. To be ſteadyard immoveable in the proſecution of wiſe and honeſt Reſolutions, by all honeſt and prudent means, is indeed a Duty that admits of no exception. But nevertheleſs it ought not to hinder that, at the ſame time, there be alſo a due care taken of preſerving a ſair Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>A good Name,</hi> ſays the Wiſe Man, <hi>is better than a Precious Oyntment.</hi> It is a Perfume that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends the Perſon whom it accompanies, that procures him every where an eaſy Acceptance, and that facilitates the Succeſs of all his Enterpriſes. And for that reaſon, tho' there were no other, I intreat you to obſerve, that the care of a Mans Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an eſſential part of that very ſame Duty that ingages him in the purſuit of any worthy Defign.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not entertain you with a Declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon this general Theme. My buſineſs is to repreſent to you, more particularly, thoſe very Imputations which are caſt upon your Self, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome of their evident Conſequences; that, if poſſible, I may thereby move you to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour after a Remedy. The Source of all ariſes from the ordinary Acceſs you have unto the King, the Credit you are ſuppoſed to have with Him, and the deep Jealouſy that ſome People have conceived of His Intentions in reference to Religion. Their Jealouſy is, that his Aim has been to ſettle Popery in this Nation, not onely in a fair and ſecure Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but even in a predominating Superiority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175324:3"/>all other Profeſſions. And from hence the inference follows, that Whoſoever has any par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Councels of this Reign, muſt needs be Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected: But, that to have ſo great a part of them, as you are ſaid to have had, can happen to none but an abſolute Papiſt. That is the direct Charge. But that is not enough. Your Poſt is too conſiderable for a Papiſt of an ordinary ſorm: and therefore you muſt be a Jeſuit. Nay to confirm that Suggeſtion, it muſt be accompanied with all the circumſtances that may beſt give it an Air of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability; as that you have been bred at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in the Jeſuits Colledge; that you have taken Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at <hi>Rome,</hi> and there obtained a Diſpenſation to Marry; and that you have, ſince then, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly officiated as a Prieſt, in the Celebration of the Maſs, at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and other Places. And this being admitted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can be too black to caſt upon you. Whatſoever thought amiſs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State, the never ſo contrary to your Advice, is boldly attributed to it. And if other Proofs fail, the Scripture it ſelf muſt be brought in to confirm, <hi>That whoſoever of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends in one Point,</hi> (in a Point eſpecially ſo eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial as that of our too-much-affected Uniformity) <hi>is guilty of the Breach of all our Laws.</hi> Thus the Charge of Popery draws after it a Tail, like the <hi>Et-caetera</hi>-Oath, and, by endleſs Iunuendo's, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicates you as guilty of whatſoever Malice can invent, or Folly believe. But that Charge therefore being removed, the Inferences that are drawn from it will vaniſh, and your Reputation will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily return to its former Brightneſs.</p>
            <p>Now, that I may the more effectually perſwade you to apply ſome Remedy to this Diſeaſe, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Sir, ſuffer me to lay before you ſome of its pernicious Conſequences. It is no trifling matter for a Perſon raiſed, as you are, above the common level, to lie under the Prejudice of ſo general a Miſtake, in ſo Important a Matter. The general, and the long, prevalency of any Opinion gives it a ſtrength, eſpecially amongſt the Vulgar, that is not eaſily ſhaken. And as it happens that you have alſo Enemies of a higher Rank, who will be ready to improve ſuch popular Miſtakes, by all ſorts of malicious Artifices, It muſt be taken for granted that thoſe Errors will be thereby ſtill more confirmed, and the Inconveniencies that may ariſe from thence no leſs increaſed. This, Sir, I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure you, is a melancholy Proſpect to your Friends. For we know you have ſuch Enemies. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ign of ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Principles have lead you to promote, has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many of thoſe whoſe Intereſt it is to croſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I need not tell you how many, and how pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful they are. Nor can I tell you, either how far, or by what Ways and Means, they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to execute their Revenge. But this how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I muſt needs tell you, That in your preſent Circumſtances, there is ſufficient ground for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much Jealouſie, at leaſt, as ought to excite you to uſe the Precaution of ſome publick Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. This the Tenderneſs of Friendſhip prompts your Friends to deſire of you; And this the juſt Senſe of your Honour, which true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does not extinguiſh, requires you to execute.</p>
            <p>Pardon, I intreat you, Sir, the earneſtneſs of theſe Expreſſions; nay ſuffer me, without Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to expoſtulate with you yet a little farther. I am fearful leſt theſe perſonal Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould not have their due weight with you; and therefore I cannot omit to reflect alſo upon ſome more general Conſequences of your particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Reproach. I have ſaid it already, <hi>That the King, His Honour, His Government, and even the Peace and Settlement of this whole Nation, either are, or have been concerned in this matter.</hi> Your Reputation, as you are ſaid to have medled in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs, has been of publick Concernment. The promoting a General Liberty of Conſcience having been your particular Province, The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> that has been caſt upon you, has reflected upon His Majeſty; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made uſe, in that Affair, of ſo diſguiſed a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage as you are ſuppoſed to have been. It has alſo weakned the force of all your Endeavours, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed their Effect, and contributed greatly to diſappoint this poor Nation of that ineſtimable Happineſs, and ſecure Eſtabliſhment, which I am perſwaded you deſigned, and which all good and wiſe Men agree that a <hi>juſt and inviolable Liberty of Conſcience</hi> would infallibly produce. I heartily wiſh this Conſideration had been ſooner laid to Heart, and that ſome demonſtrative Evidence, of your Sincerity in the Profeſſion you make, had accompanied all your endeavours for Liberty.</p>
            <p>But what do I ſay, or what do I wiſh for? I confeſs that I am now ſtruck with Aſtoniſhment, at that abundant Evidence, which I know you have conſtantly given, of the Oppoſition of your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; and at the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Regard there has been had unto it. If an open
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175324:3"/>Profeſſion of the directeſt Oppoſition againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, that has ever appeared in the World, ſince Popery was firſt diſtinguiſhed from common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, would ſerve the turn, this cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to all thoſe of that Society, with which you are joyned in the Duties of Religious Worſhip. If to have maintained the Principles of that Society, by frequent and ſervent Diſcourſes, by many ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Writings, by ſuffering Ignominy, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and other manifold Diſadvantages in defence thereof, can be admitted as any proof of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Adherence thereunto, this, it is evident to the World, you have done already. Nay further, If to have enquired as far as was poſſible for you, into the particular Stories that have been framed againſt you, and to have ſought all means of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying the Miſtakes upon which they were grounded, could in any meaſure avail to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a true Character of you in mens Judgments, this alſo I know you have done.<note place="margin">Dr. Tillot ſon.</note> For I have ſeen under the Hand of a Reverend Dean of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, a full acknowledgement of Satisfaction received from you, in a ſuſpiciou he had entertained, upon one of thoſe Stories, and to which his Report had procured too great Credit. And though I know you are averſe to the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Letter without his expreſs leave, and perhaps may not now think fit to ask it, yet I am ſo thoroughly aſſured of his Sincerity and Candor, that I cannot doubt but he has already vindicated you in that matter, and will (according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs) be ſtill ready to do it upon all Occaſions. Nay, I have ſeen alſo your Juſtification from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Calumny of common Fame, about your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kidnapp'd one who had been formerly a <hi>Monk,</hi> out of your <hi>American</hi> Province, to deliver him here into the Hands of his Enemies; I ſay, I have ſeen your Juſtification from that Story under that Perſons own Hand: And his return to <hi>Penſylvania,</hi> where he now reſides, may be an irrefragable Confutation of it, to any that will take the pains to inquire thereinto.</p>
            <p>Really it afflicts me very much to conſider that all this does not ſuffice. If I had not that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſpect for you, which I ſincerely profeſs, yet I could not but be much affected, that any man who had deſervedly acquired ſo fair a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as you have formerly had, whoſe Integrity and Veracity had always been reputed ſpotleſs, and whoſe Charity had been continually exerciſed in ſerving others, at the dear expence of his Time, his Strength, and his Eſtate, without any other Recompence than what reſults from the conſciouſneſs of doing good, I ſay, I could not but be much affected to ſee any ſuch Perſon fall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently and undeſervedly, under ſuch unjuſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches as you have done. It is a hard caſe, and I think no man, that has any Bowels of Humanity, can reſlect upon it without great Relentings.</p>
            <p>Since therefore it is ſo, and that ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains yet to be done, ſomething more expreſs, and eſpecially more publick, than has yet been doue for your Vindieation, I beg of you, Dear Sir, by all the tender Efficacy that Friendſhip, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mine, or that of all your Friends and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons together, can have upon you; by the due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard which Humanity and even Chriſtianity ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges you to have to your Reputation; by the Duty you owe unto the King; by your Love unto the Land of your Nativity; and by the Cauſe of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Religion and Eternal Truth; Let not the Scandal of Infincerity, that I have hinted at, lye any longer upon you; but let the Senſe of all theſe Obligations perſwade you to gratifie your Friends and Relations, and to ſerve your King, your Country, and your Religion, by ſuch a publick Vindication of your Honour as your own Prudence, upon theſe Suggeſtions, will now ſhew you to be moſt neceſſary and moſt expedient. I am, with unfeigned and moſt reſpectful Affection,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>October the 20th.</hi> 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Honoured Sir, Your moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:175324:4"/>
            <head>Mr. PENN's ANSWER To the foregoing LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is now above twenty Years, I thank God, that I have not been very ſolicitous what the World thought of me. For ſince I have had the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Religion from a Principle</hi> in <hi>my Self,</hi> the firſt and main Point with me, has been to approve my Self in the ſight of God, through Patience and Welldoing: ſo that the <hi>World</hi> has not had weight enough with me, to ſuffer its good Opinion to raiſe me, or its ill Opinion to deject me. And if that had been the only Motive or Conſideration, and not the deſire of a good Friend, in the name of many others. I had been as ſilent to thy Letter as I uſe to be to the Idle and Maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Shams</hi> of the Times. But as the Laws of <hi>Friendſtip</hi> are ſacred with thoſe that value that Relation, ſo I confeſs this to be a Principle One with me, not to deny a Friend the ſattisfaction he defires, when it may be done without offence to a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Buſineſs chiefly inliſted upon, is my <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> and endeavours to promote it. I do ſay then, and that with all Sincerity, that I am not only no <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> but no <hi>Papiſt.</hi> And which is more, I never had any Temptation upon me to be it, either from doubts in my own mind about the way I profeſs, or from the diſcourſes or writings of any of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And in the Preſence of Almighty. God I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the King did never once, directly or indirectly, attack me, or tempt me upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the many Years that I have had the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a free Acceſs to him; ſo unjuſt, as well as ſordidly falſe, are all thoſe Storys of the Town.</p>
            <p>The only Reaſon, that I can apprehend, they have to repute me a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> is my frequent going to <hi>Whitehall;</hi> a place no more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to me than to the reſt of the World, who yet, it ſeems, find much ſairer Quarter. I have almoſt continually had one Buſineſs or other there for our Friends, whom I ever ſerved with a ſteady Solicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thro all times ſince I was of their Communion. I had alſo a great many perſonal good Offices to do upon a Principle of Charity, for People of all perſwaſions; thinking it a Duty to improve the little Intereſt I had, for the good of thoſe that needed it, eſpecially the <hi>Poor.</hi> I might add ſomething of my own Aſſairs too; though I muſt own, (if I may without vanity) that they have ever had the leaſt ſhare of my Thoughts or Pains, or elſe they would not have ſtill depended as they yet do.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175324:4"/>
            <p>But becauſe ſome People are ſe unjuſt as to render, Inſtances for my <hi>Popery</hi> (or <hi>Hipocriſy</hi> rather, for ſo it would be in me) 'tis fit I contradict them as particularly as they accuſe me. I ſay then ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, that I am ſo far from having been bred at St. <hi>Omers</hi> and having received Orders at <hi>Rome,</hi> that I never was at either Place; nor do I know any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy there; nor had I ever a Correſpondency with any one in thoſe Places, which is another Story invented againſt me. And as for my officiating in the <hi>Kings Chappel,</hi> or any other, it is ſo ridiculous as well as untrue, that beſides that no body can do it but a Prieſt, and that I have been marryed to a Woman of ſome Condition above ſixteen Years, which no Prieſt can be, by any Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation whatever, I have not ſo much as <hi>lookt</hi> into any Chappell of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, and conſequently not the Kings; though a common curioſity warrants it daily to People of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions.</p>
            <p>And once for all, I do ſay that I am a <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenter,</hi> and to that degree ſuch, that I challenge the moſt celebrated Proteſtant of the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> or any other, upon that Head, be he <hi>Lay-man</hi> or <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-Man,</hi> in <hi>Publick</hi> or in <hi>Private.</hi> For I would have ſuch People know, 'tis not impoſſible for a <hi>True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenter</hi> to be <hi>Dutiful, Thankful,</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable</hi> to the King, though he be of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Communion. We hold not our <hi>Property</hi> or <hi>Protection</hi> from Him by our <hi>Perſwaſion,</hi> and therefore His <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> ſhould not be the Meaſure of our <hi>Allegiance.</hi> I am ſorry to ſee ſo many that ſeem fond of the Reformed Religion, by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection to Him, recommend it ſo ill. Whatever, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> we might reaſonably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt (and we know ſuch there are) yet He has diſclaim'd and reprehended thoſe ill things, by His <hi>declared Opinion</hi> againſt Perſecution; by the Eaſe in which He actually indulges all Diſſenters; and by the Confirmation he offers in Parliament for the <hi>Security of the Proteſtant Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience.</hi> And in His Honour, as well as in my own Deſence, I am obliged in Conſcience to ſay that he has ever declared to me it was His Opinion; and on all occaſions, when <hi>Duke,</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver refuſed me the repeated Proofs of it, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as I had any <hi>Poor Sufferer for Conſcience ſake</hi> to ſollicit His help for.</p>
            <p>But ſome may be apt to ſay, <hi>Why not any Body elſe as well as well as I? Why muſt I have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable acceſs to other Diſſenters, if not a Papiſt? I</hi> Anſwer, I know not that it is ſo. But this I know, that I have made it my Province and Buſineſs; I have followed and preſt it; I took it for my Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Station, and have kept it above theſe ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years; and which is more, (if I may ſay it without <hi>Vanity</hi> or <hi>Reproach</hi>) wholly at my own Charges too. To this let me add the Relation my Father had to this Kings Service; his particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in getting me releaſed out of the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in 69; my <hi>Fathers</hi> humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to Him upon his <hi>Death-Bed</hi> to protect me from the Inconveniences and Troubles my Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion might expoſe me to; and His Friendly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to do it, and exact Performance of it, from the moment I addreſſed my ſelf to Him; I ſay, when all this is conſidered, any Body that has the leaſt pretence to <hi>Good Nature, Gratitude,</hi> or <hi>Generoſity,</hi> muſt needs know how to interpret my Acceſs to the King.</p>
            <p>Perhaps ſome will be ready to ſay this is not all, nor is this yet a fault, but that I have been an Adviſer in other matrers, diſguſtful to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and which tend to the Overthrow of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and the Liberties of the People. A likely thing indeed, that a <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenter,</hi> who from fifteen Years old has been (at times) a Sufferer, <hi>in his Father's Family, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverfity, and by the Government,</hi> for being ſo, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion! This is juſt as probable, as it is true that I <hi>dy'd a Jeſuit</hi> ſix years ago in <hi>America.</hi> Will men ſtill ſuffer ſuch Stuff to paſs upon them? Is any thing more fooliſh, as well as falſe, than that becauſe I am often at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> the refore I muſt be Author of all that is done there that does not pleaſe abroad? But ſuppoſing ſome ſuch things to have been done; pray tell me, if I am bound to oppoſe any thing that I am not call'd to do? I never was a Member of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Cabinet,</hi> or <hi>Committee,</hi> where the Affairs of the Kingdom are tranſacted. I have had no Office or Truſt, and conſequently nothing can be ſaid to be done by me; nor, for that reaſon, could I lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any <hi>Teſt</hi> or Obligation to diſcover my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Publick Acts of State; and therefore, neither can any ſuch Acts, or my Silence about them, in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be made my Crime. <hi>Volunteers</hi> are <hi>Blanks</hi> and <hi>Cyphers</hi> in all Governments. And unleſs calling at <hi>White-Hall</hi> once a day, upon many Occaſions, or my not being turn'd out of nothing, (for that no Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is) be the Evidence of my Compliance in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable thingt, I know not what elſe can with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175324:5"/>any Truth be aledged againſt me. However, one thing I know, that I have every where moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly obſerv'd, and endeavour'd in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Perſons of all Ranks and Opinions, to allay Heats, and moderate Extremities, even in the Politicks. 'Tis below me to be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. But I am ſure it has been my endeavour, that if we could not all meet upon a Religious Bottom, at leaſt we might meet upon a <hi>Civil One, the good of England;</hi> which is the common intereſt of King and People: That He might be great by Juſtice, and we free by Obedience; diſtinguiſhing rightly on the one hand, between <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and on the other, between <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, alas, I am not without my Apprehenſions of the Cauſe of this behaviour towards me, and in this I perceive we agree; I mean, my <hi>conſtant Zeal for an Impartial Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> But if that be it, the Cauſe is too good to be inpain about it. I ever underſtood <hi>That</hi> to be the natural Right of all men; and that he that had a Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, his Religion was none of his own. For what is not the Religion of a mans choice, is the Religion of him that impoſes it. So that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is the firſt <hi>Step</hi> to have a Religion. This is no new Opinion with me. I have writ many <hi>Apologies</hi> within the laſt twenty Years to defend it, and that impartially. Yet I have as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly declared, that Bounds ought to be ſet to this Freedom, and that <hi>Morality</hi> was the beſt; and that as often as <hi>That</hi> was violated under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Conſcience, it was fit the <hi>Civil Power</hi> ſhould take place. Nor did I ever once think of promoting any ſort of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body, which did not preſerve the Common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy of the Kingdom, and the Antient Rights of the Government: For to ſay Truth, the one cannot be maintained without the other.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter, I muſt ſay, I love <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> I ever did ſo; and that I am not in her Debt. I never valued <hi>Time, Money,</hi> or <hi>Kindred,</hi> to ſerve her and do her good. No Party could ever byaſs me to her Prejudice, nor any Perſonal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt oblige me in her wrong. For I always ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd <hi>diſcounting Private Favours at the Publicks Coſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would I have made my Matket of the Fears and Jealouſies of People, when this King came to the Crown, I had put <hi>Twenty Thouſand Pounds</hi> into my Pocket, and a <hi>Hundred Thouſand</hi> into my Province. For mighty numbers of People were then upon the Wing. But I wav'd it all; hop'd for better Times; expected the Effects of the Kings Word for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and Happineſs by it; and till I ſaw my own Friends, with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, deliver'd from the <hi>Legal Bondage,</hi> which <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws</hi> for Religion had ſubjected them to, I could with no Satisfaction think of leaving <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> though much to my Prejudice beyond Set, and at my great Expence here; having in all this time, never had either Office or Penſion, and refuſing ever the Rewards or Gratuities of thoſe I have been able to oblige.</p>
            <p>If therefore an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Charity,</hi> if the aſſerting an <hi>Impartial Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> if <hi>doing to others as one would be done by,</hi> and an open avowing, and ſteady practiſing of theſe things, in all times, to all Parties, will juſtly lay a Man under the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> or <hi>Papiſt</hi> of any Rank, I muſt not only ſubmit to the <hi>Character,</hi> but imbrace it too; And, I care not who knows, I can wear it with more Pleaſure, than it is poſſible for them with any Juſtice to give it me. For theſe are <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Stones and Principles</hi> with me; and I am ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized at all Buildings that have them not for their Foundations. For Religion it ſelf is an empty Name without them; <hi>A Whited-Wall; a Painted-Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre;</hi> No Life or Virtue to the Soul; No good or Example to ones Neighbour. Let us not flatter our Selves; <hi>We can never be the better for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> if our <hi>Neighbour he the worſe for it.</hi> Our fault is, we are apt to be mighty hot upon ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Errors, and break all Bounds in our Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but we let practical ones paſs without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, if not without Repentance: As if a miſtake about an obſcure Propoſition of Faith were a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evil, than the breach of an undoubted Precept. Such a Religion the Devils themſelves are not without; for they have both Faith and Knowledge: but their Faith doth not work by Love, nor their Knowledge by Obedience. And if this be their Judgment, can it be our Bleſſing?</p>
            <p>Let us not then think Religion a litigious thing; nor that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came onely to make us good Diſputants, but that he came alſo to make us good Livers. Sincerity goes farther than Capacity. It is Charity that deſervedly excels in the <hi>Chriſtian Relegion.</hi> And happy would it be, if where <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> ends, <hi>Charity</hi> did begin, inſtead of Envy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175324:5"/>and Railing, that almoſt ever follow? It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me to be the way that God has found out and appointed to moderate our Differences, and make them at leaſt harmleſs to Society; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I confeſs, I dare not aggravate them to Wrath and Blood. Our Diſagreement lies in our Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, or belief of things; and if the common Enemy of Mankind had not the governing of our Affections and Paſſions, that Diſagreement would not prove ſuch a Canker, as it is, to Love and Peace in Civil Societies.</p>
            <p>He that ſuffers his Difference with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>about the other World,</hi> to carry him beyond the Line of <hi>Moderation, in this,</hi> is the worſe for his Opinion, <hi>even though it be true.</hi> It is too little conſidered by Chriſtians, that men may <hi>hold the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrightcouſneſs;</hi> that they may be Orthodox and not know what Spirit they are of. So were the Diſciples of our Lord. They believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, yet let a falſe Zeal do violence to their Judgment, and their unwarrantable heat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the great end of their Saviours coming, <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men may be angry for God's ſake, and kill People too. Chriſt ſaid it, and too many have practiſed it. But what ſort of Chriſtians muſt they be, I pray, that can hate in his Name who bids us love, and kill for his ſake, that forbids killing, and commands love, even to Enemies.</p>
            <p>Let not Men or Parties think to ſhift it off from themſelves. 'Tis not this Principle, or that Form, to which ſo great a Defection is owing, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy of Mind from God. Chriſtianity is not at Heart: No Fear of God in the inward parts: No aw of his Divine Omnipreſence. Self prevails, and breaks out, more or leſs, through all Forms, but too plainly: (Pride, Wrath, Luſt, Avarice:) ſo that though People ſay to God, <hi>Thy Will be done,</hi> they do their own: Which ſhews them to be true Heathens under a mask of Chriſtianity; that believe without Works, and repent without forſaking: bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for Forms, and the Temporal Benefits of them; while true Religion, which is <hi>to Viſit the Fatherleſs and the Widow, and to keep our ſelves unſpotted from the World,</hi> goes barefoot, and like <hi>Lazarus</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. Yet this was the Definition the Holy Ghoſt gave of Religion before <hi>Synods</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> had the <hi>meddling</hi> with it, and <hi>modeling</hi> of it. In thoſe days <hi>Bowels</hi> were a good part of Religion, and that to the <hi>Fatherleſs</hi> and <hi>Widow,</hi> at large. We can hardly now extend them to thoſe of our own way.</p>
            <p>It was ſaid by him that could not ſay amiſs, <hi>Becauſe Iniquity abounds the Love of many waxes cold.</hi> What ſoever divides man's Heart from God, ſeparates it from his Neighbour; and he that loves <hi>ſelf more than God,</hi> can never <hi>love his Neighbour as himſelf,</hi> For (as the Apoſtle ſaid) <hi>if we do not love him whom we ſee, how can we love God whom we have not ſeen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that we could ſee ſome men as eager to turn People to God, as they are to blow them up, and ſet them one againſt another. But indeed thoſe only can have that pure and pious Zeal, who are themſelves turned to God, and have taſted the ſweetneſs of that Converſion, which is to Power not Form, to Godlineſs not Gain. Such as thoſe do bend their thoughts and pains to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe, not increaſe, Heats and Animoſities; to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort People to look at home, ſweep their own Houſes, and weed their own Gardens. And in no Age or Time was there more need to ſet men to work in their own Heart, than this we live in; when ſo buſie, wandering, unruly, and licentious a Spirit prevails. For whatever ſome men may think, <hi>The Diſeaſe of this Kingdom is Sin,</hi> Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt God, and want of Charity to men. And while this Guilt lies at our Door, Judgment cannot be far off.</p>
            <p>Now this being the Diſeaſe, I will briefly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer two things for Cure of it. The firſt is, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids clean Heart and right Spirit,</hi> which he aſk'd and had of God. Without this we muſt be a <hi>Chaos</hi> ſtill. For the Diſtemper is within; and our Lord ſaid, <hi>All Evil comes from thence.</hi> Set the inward Man right, and the outward man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wrong. That is the Helm that governs the humane Veſſel. And this nothing can do but an inward Principle, the <hi>Light and Grace that came by Chriſt,</hi> which the Scripture tells us <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens every one, and has appeared to all men.</hi> It is prepoſterous to think that he, who made the World, ſhould ſhow leaſt care of the beſt part of it, our Souls. No, he that gave us an outward Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary for our Bodies, hath given us an inward one for our Minds to act, by. We have it: And 'tis our Condemnation that we don't love it, and bring our Deeds to it. 'Tis by this we ſee our Sins, are made ſenſible of them, ſorry for them, and finally forſake them. And he that thinks to go to Heaven a nearer way will, I fear, belate his Soul, and be irreparably miſtaken. There are but <hi>Goats and Sheep</hi> at laſt; whatever ſhapes we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175324:6"/>wear here. Let's not therefore, Dear Friend, deceive our ſelves. <hi>Our Souls are at Stake. God won't be mocked. What we ſow we muſt expect to reap. There is no Repentance in the Grave;</hi> which ſhows, that if not there, then no where elſe.</p>
            <p>To ſum up this Divinity of mine, It is the Light of Jeſus in our Souls that gives us a true ſight of our ſelves, and that Sight that leads us to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which Repentance begets Humility, and Humility that true Charity that covers a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Faults; which I call God's Expedient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt man's Infirmity.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Remedy to our preſent Diſtemper is this, Since All of all Parties profeſs to <hi>believe in God, Chriſt, the Spirit, and Scripture, that the Soul is Immortal, that there are Eternal Rewards and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and that the Vertuous ſhall receive the one, and the Wicked ſuffer the other;</hi> I ſay, ſince this is the common Faith of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> let us all reſolve in the ſtrength of God to <hi>live up to what we agree in, before we fall out ſo miſerably about the reſt in which we differ.</hi> I am perſwaded, the Change and Comfort which that pious courſe would bring us to, would go very far to diſpoſe our Natures to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound eaſily for all the reſt; and we might hope yet to ſee happy days in poor <hi>England:</hi> for there I would have ſo good a Work begun. And how it is poſſible for the Eminent Men of every religious Perſwaſion, (eſpecially the preſent Miniſters of the Pariſhes of <hi>ENGLAND</hi>) to think of giving an Account to God at the laſt day, without uſing the utmoſt of their Endeavours to moderate the members of their reſpective Communions towards thoſe that differ from them, is a Myſtery to me. But this I know, and muſt lay it at their Doors, as I charge alſo my own Soul with it, God requires Moderation, and Humility from us: For he is at hand who will not ſpare to judge our Impatiency, if we have no Patience for one another. The Eternal God rebuke (I beſeech him) the wrath of man; and humble All under the ſenſe of the Evil of this day; and yet (unworthy as we are) give us Peace, for his holy Name's ſake.</p>
            <p>It is now time to end this Letter; and I will do it without ſaying any more than this. Thou ſeeſt my Defence againſt popular Calumny; Thou ſeeſt what my thoughts are of our Condition, and the way to better it; and thou ſeeſt my hearty and humble Prayer to Almighty God to incline us to be wiſe, if it were but for our own ſakes. I ſhall only add, that I am extreamly ſenſible of the Kindneſs and Juſtice intended me by my Friends on this Occaſion; and that I am for that and many more reaſons, with great Truth and Eſteem,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>TEDDINGTON,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>October the 24th.</hi> 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy obliged and affectionate Friend, <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ONe thing in reference to my ſelf I forgot to mention, I have been by ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with great art rendred powerful, that I might be made guilty, at leaſt obnoxious; which hath often drawn from me this Expreſſion to my Acquaintance: I have all the Inconvenience of a man of Power and Intereſt, but nothing of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity or advantage of that Character. One thing I will ſay, and end; I muſt do as I would be done by, and cannot with fine Diſtinctions or popular Humor, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve my ſelf from that Duty; for, I thank God, I am what I was, and will be what I am, with his help, let the World ſay what it will, <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175324:6"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
